A Guide to the Brian H. Ford Colonial Village Collection, 1936-2004
Arlington Public Library, Center for Local History
Arlington Public Library, Center for Local History
Brian H. Ford Colonial Village Collection, 1936-2004
Arlington Public Library, Center for Local History
RG 325
2 boxes.
Ford, Brian H.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
The collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Brian H. Ford.
Historical Information
Colonial Village, built in 1936, was the first apartment complex built in Arlington during the Great Depression. Located near the shopping area of Clarendon and the County's government center in Courthouse, it has long served as a popular residence for Arlingtonians. In the 1970s, Colonial Village was purchased by Mobil Land Corporation and was considered for significant redevelopment. The residents of Colonial Village came together to save their homes, and various committees were formed to list the complex as a local, state, and national historic district. On December 5, 1978, Colonial Village earned its historic designation and continues to be an important landmark in Arlington.
Scope and Content
RG 325 is made up of materials collected and created by Brian H. Ford, a resident of Colonial Village. This collection dates from 1936 to 2004, with the bulk of materials situated in the late 1970s and early 1980s, and measures .83 linear feet. Most of these materials relate to the efforts of residents and the Colonial Village Preservation Committee to add Colonial Village to the National Register of Historic Places and as a local historic district, which can be found in Series 2, Colonial Village Preservation Committee. Series 5, Historical Research, contains Ford's outside research on Colonial Village, focusing on its pre-1970 history. There are also several folders of newspaper clippings from the 1970s that mention Colonial Village and a few personal materials about Brian Ford and his Colonial Village home. There are seventeen black and white photographs of the complex taken in 1978 and several maps.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into ten series arranged by subject and type of material. Material within each series is sorted chronologically. Series 1, Correspondence, has two subseries: from the Arlington County Board to Colonial Village, and Colonial Village to residents. Folder titles are created by the processor; any portion of a folder title in quotes ("") reference a title to a report or article.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Material
RG 372, Nnoka Colonial Village Collection
Index Terms
Subjects:
Colonial Village (Arlington, Va.); Apartments -- Conservation and restoration; Arlington (Va.); Arlington County (Va.)
Contents List
- Correspondence
  - Correspondence to Colonial Village from Arlington County Board
    - Colonial Village - Arlington County Board Correspondence, 1978-1979 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence to Residents
    - Correspondence to Colonial Village Residents by Property Owners, 1977-1986 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence from Mobil Land Corporation to Colonial Village Tenants, 1978-1979 (Box 1)
- Colonial Village Preservation Committee
  - Colonial Village Preservation Comittee Bylaws and Letterhead, n.d. (Box 1)
  - Colonial Village Preservation Committee Correspondence, 1978 (Box 1)
  - Petitions for Colonial Village as an Historic Site, n.d. (Box 1)
  - Correspondence relating to National Register of Historic Places for Colonial Village, 1978-1981 (Box 1)
  - Colonial Village National Register of Historic Places Application and Application Materials, 1978 (Box 1)
  - Colonial Village Preservation Committee Correspondence, 1978 (Box 1)
  - Colonial Village Preservation Committee News Releases, 1978 (Box 1)
  - Colonial Village Preservation Committee Bylaws and Contacts, 1978, n.d. (Box 1)
  - Colonial Village Preservation Committee Publications: Urban Land, Architectural Forum and Record, National Geographic, Mortgage Banker, 1938, 1939, 1948 (Box 1)
  - Arlington County and the National Register of Historic Places Pamphlet, 2001 (Box 1)
  - "Colonial Village: Its Cultural History, Architectural Quality, and Significance" Appendix II, May 25, 1978 (Box 1)
  - "Colonial Village - The Cultural and Architectural Heritage" Preliminary Report, May 25, 1978 (Box 1)
  - "Colonial Village - The Cultural and Architecural Heritage" Revised, November 10, 1978 (Box 1)
- Colonial Village Site Plan Committee
  - Colonial Village Site Plan, 1978 (Box 2)
  - Colonial Village Site Plan Review Committee Materails, 1978-1979 (Box 2)
- Colonial Village Tenants Association
  - Colonial Village Tenants Association Resident Survey, April 1981 (Box 2)
- Publications
  - "Apartment Seekers Guide to Arlington" Booklet (Box 2)
  - Colonial Village Brochures, n.d. (Box 2)
- Research on Colonial Village
  - Research on Colonial Village before 1970, 1935, n.d. (Box 2)
  - Historic Research on Colonial Village, 1934-1959, 1976 (Box 2)
  - Colonial Village Research Citations (Box 2)
- Photographs
  - Biographical sketch and photograph of Harvey Warwick, Sr., 1982, n.d. (Box 2)
  - Colonial Village Photographs and Negatives 1978 (Box 2)
- Newspaper Clippings/News
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1973-1978 (1) (Box 2)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1973-1978 (2) (Box 2)
  - Newspaper Clippings about Colonial Village, 1979-1981 (Box 2)
- Reports about Colonial Village
  - Insured Mortgage for Colonial Village 1936-1944 (Box 2)
  - Brian H. Ford's Lease for Colonial Village 1977 (Box 2)
  - Report - "Changes in Rent at Colonial Village Since 1936" by Fred Berghoefer, 1979 (Box 2)
  - Assessment Verification List of Properties in Arlington, February 26, 1979 (Box 2)
  - Colonial Village Promotional Materials - Brochure and Site Plan (Box 2)
  - Letter to "Qualified Tenants," May 2, 1989 (Box 2)
  - Wesley Housing Development Corporation Summary of Activities, Fiscal Year 1998 (Box 2)
  - Report - "Issues with Parnell Apartment at Colonial Village," 2004 (Box 2)
- Maps
  - Photocopied Maps of Colonial Village, n.d. (Box 2)
  - Maps (Box (OV))